Empire Ranch records, 1874-1944 (bulk 1880-1916)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Empire Ranch records, 1874-1944 (bulk 1880-1916)
AZ 246
Empire Ranch (Ariz.)
This collection includes correspondence, legal documents, financial records, livestock records, and other materials relating to the history, development, and operation of ranch property in Southern Arizona and California. Includes records of cattle companies associated with the Empire Ranch. Some ranches covered are Onyx Ranch, Bonita Ranch, El Dorado Ranch, Rosemont Ranch, Pantano Ranch, and Rancho Corral de Quati.
7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Empire Ranch is located east of Tucson. Started in 1876 by Walter L. Vail, founder of the Empire Land and Cattle Company, it became one of the largest cattle ranches in Arizona. In 1886, Vail formed a partnership with Carrol W. Gates. Soon after Vail and Gates expanded land and cattle operations to California, Kansas, and Oklahoma. Their headquarters were the Empire Ranch and Warner's Ranch in California. Chiricahua Ranches Company purchased the Empire Ranch operations in 1928.
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series:
Series I: Papers of the 1870's and Personal Material, 1874-1916
Series II: Empire Land and Cattle Co. Records, 1880-1934
Series III: Miscellaneous Property Records, 1876-1916
Series IV: Crittenden Cattle Co. Records, 1881-1938
Series V: Chiricahua Cattle Co. Records, 1885-1911
Series VI: Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Co. Records, 1917-1928
Series VII: Doyle Cattle Co. Records, 1926-1929
Series VIII: Chiricahua Ranches Co. Records, 1927-1944
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence, legal documents, financial records, livestock records, and other materials relating to the history, development, and operation of ranch property in Southern Arizona and California. Includes records of cattle companies associated with the Empire Ranch. Some ranches covered are Onyx Ranch, Bonita Ranch, El Dorado Ranch, Rosemont Ranch, Pantano Ranch, and Rancho Corral de Quati. Also present are land and mining papers including Arizona land patents, land grant materials, abstracts of titles, and papers relating to mines such as the Total Wreck Mine. Abstracts of title involve land of the Whetstone and San Pedro Land and Cattle Co., Arivaca Land and Cattle Co., Las Jarillas Cattle Co. and others.
Vail, Walter L., 1852-1906; Vail, Edward L., 1849-1936; Gates, Carrol W., d. 1920; Empire Land and Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence; Crittenden Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence; Chiricahua Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence; Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence; Chiricahua Ranches Company -- Records and correspondence; Doyle Cattle Company -- Records and correspondence; Whetstone and San Pedro Land and Cattle Company (Ariz.); Arivaca Land and Cattle Company; Las Jarillas Cattle Company; Vail and Gates (Firm) -- Records and correspondence; United States. Forest Service. Sierra Forest Reserve; Warner's Ranch (Calif.); Total Wreck Mine (Ariz.); Cattle trade -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Sheep industry -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Cattle trade -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Cattle trade -- California -- History -- Sources; Forest reserves -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Land titles -- Arizona -- History -- Sources; Land grants -- Arizona; Ranches -- Arizona -- Records and correspondence; Babocamari Land Grant; San Jose de Sonoita Land Grant; Correspondence; Account books; Ledgers; Land grants
Container List
- Series I: Papers of the 1870's and Personal Material, 1874-1916
  - Papers of the 1870's including legal papers and live stock sales. ca. 1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership receipts in American National Live Stock Association. 1902-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Associated Charities of Los Angeles. 1896-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - YMCA Committee of Safety, Los Angeles. 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Papers of the Arizona Cattle Grower's Association. 1904-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment of Walter L. Vail as Live Stock Sanitary Commissioner of Arizona by Governor N. O. Murphy. February 15, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal correspondence. 1887-1916 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Series II: Empire Land and Cattle Co. Records, 1880-1934
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Letter Book (Edward L. Vail). 1898-1900 (Box 1)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Letter Book (Carroll W. Gates). 1898-1900 (Box 1)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Letter Book (Edward L. Vail). 1899 (Box 1)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Ledger no. 2. 1894-1898 (Volume 2)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Ledger no. 3. 1899-1905 (Volume 3)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Ledger no. 4. 1899-1905 (Volume 4)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Index to Ledger no. 4 (2 copies). 1899-1905 (Volume 5)
  - Empire Land and Cattle Co.: Rainfall 1908 (Volume 31)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co. Livestock Papers and Financial Records, 1880-1928
    - Livestock sales (legal papers). 1880-1920 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous livestock papers including various papers of the Live Stock Sanitary Board of Arizona. 1885-1914 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous financial papers. 1880-1910, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Promissory notes. 1880-1918 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bank records including checks, deposit slips, etc. 1881-1928 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Assessments and taxes. 1884-1891, 1893, 1900-1901 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Rosemont Ranch Ledger (Edward L. Vail). 1900-1905 (Box 6)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Abstract of Lands. (Box 7)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Abstract of Titles. (Box 8)
    Documents relating to land involved in the history, development and operation of the Empire Ranch, including:
    Arivaca Land & Cattle Company
    Las Jarillas Cattle Company
    Crittenden Cattle Company
    Chiricahua Ranches Company
    Vail and Ashburn
    Southern Arizona Mining Company
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Abstract of Titles (continued from Box 8). (Box 9)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1883-1884 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1889-1908 (Box 9, Volume 2)
  - Empire Land & Cattle Co.: Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1909-1934 (Box 9, Volume 3)
- Series III: Miscellaneous Property Records, 1876-1916
  - Legal Papers, Financial Records, etc., 1884-1928
    - Babocomari Land Grant. 1896-1908 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - California Development Company. 1901 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Various California Property. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Gage Tract, Warner's Ranch. 1901-1910 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Muleshoe Cattle Company. 1922-1926 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Pantano Ranch (Vosburg and Vail). 1884-1890 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Rancho Corral de Quati, etc., California (O. M. Potts). 1902-1904 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - San Jose de Sonoita Land Grant. 1903-1907 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Vail and Ashburn Papers. 1908-1928 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Land and Mining Papers, 1876-1916
    - U. S. General Land Office: Arizona Land Patents. 1876-1898 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - U. S. General Land Office, Sierra Forest Reserve: Legal papers, correspondence, etc. 1898-1915 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - U. S. General Land Office, Sierra Forest Reserve: Land Patents. 1899-1902, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - U. S. Forest Service Permits: Correspondence, receipts, etc. 1903-1911 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Arizona Land: Legal papers. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous land papers. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Mining Papers: Total Wreck Mine, etc. 1879-1881, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Crittenden Cattle Co. Records, 1881-1938
  Formerly Crittenden Land and Cattle Co.
  - Crittenden Cattle Co.: Legal Papers including deeds, leases of school lands. 1881-1909 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Crittenden Cattle Co.: Legal Papers. 1896-1923 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Crittenden Cattle Co.: Financial Records. 1901-1915 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Crittenden Cattle Co.: Correspondence. 1901-1916 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Crittenden Cattle Co.: Miscellaneous Papers including Articles of Incorporation, Abstract of Title to lands, stock certificates, etc. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Canceled Bonds. (Box 12)
  - Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1886-1887 (Box 12, Volume 1)
  - Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1887-1901 (Box 12, Volume 2)
  - Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1903-1938 (Box 12, Volume 3)
- Series V: Chiricahua Cattle Co. Records, 1885-1911
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Minutes of meetings of Directors and Shareholders. 1885-1909 (Volume 13)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Ledger. 1890-1907 (Volume 14)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Ledger. 1907-1909 (Volume 15)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Ledger. 1907-1908? (Volume 16)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Journal-Day Book. 1889-1909 (Volume 17)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Cash Book. 1897-1902 (Volume 18)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Cash Book. 1910-1911 (Volume 19)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Stock Transfer Book. 1885-1909 (Volume 20)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Certificates of Stock. 1885-1909 (Volume 21)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Certificates of Stock. 1885-1908 (Volume 22)
  - Chiricahua Cattle Co.: Livestock Book. 1895-1906 (Volume 23)
- Series VI: Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Co. Records, 1917-1928
  - Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Co.: Stock Ledger and Journal. 1917-1920 (Volume 24)
  - Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Co.: Certificates of Stock. 1917-1919 (Volume 25)
  - Boice-Gates-Johnson Cattle Co.: Financial Accounts. 1917-1928 (Box 26)
- Series VII: Doyle Cattle Co. Records, 1926-1929
  - Doyle Cattle Co.: Ledger. 1926-1929 (Box 27)
  - Doyle Cattle Co.: Journal (Onyx Ranch, California). 1926-1929 (Box 27)
  - Doyle Cattle Co.: Financial Records (Onyx Ranch, California). (Box 27)
  - Doyle Cattle Co.: Cash Book (Onyx Ranch, California). 1926-1929 (Box 27)
  - Doyle Cattle Co.: Miscellaneous financial papers. (Box 27)
- Series VIII: Chiricahua Ranches Co. Records, 1927-1944
  - Chiricahua Ranches Co.: Journal. 1927-1929 (Volume 28)
  - Chiricahua Ranches Co.: Minutes of Board of Directors Meetings. 1927-1929 (Volume 29)
  - Chiricahua Ranches Co.: Certificates of Stock. 1933-1934 (Volume 30)